- Behind me is a Falcon 9 rocket.
原作者名: Spacing Out with The Everyday Astronaut
视频来源: www.facebook.com/738102993243948/videos/754291784958402
原视频发布日期: 20180613
字幕翻译/压制: 旋火
- 在我身后是一枚猎鹰9号火箭
Now, with these things taking off every two weeks or so--
现在 这些东西差不多每两周就会起飞一次
- 男声: 升空
- MAN: Liftoff!
- --taking payloads to the International Space Station,
- 携带有效载荷前往国际空间站
maybe putting a satellite up into orbit,
也许把卫星送入轨道
or perhaps even a car,
甚至可能是一辆车
it's pretty easy to forget just how revolutionary this rocket really is.
很容易忘记这枚火箭到底有多大的革命性
But why is it so cool?
但为什么它这么酷？
Well, it's not just its awesome name.
不仅仅是它的名字很酷
It's also the fact that this rocket can actually land.
还在于这枚火箭可以真正着陆
Let's take a moment to appreciate just how mind-blowingly awesome this is.
让我们花点时间来欣赏一下这有多么令人震惊的威力
Okay, so how on earth do Falcon 9 rockets land?
好吧 那么猎鹰9号火箭到底是怎么着陆的呢？
What are the mechanics?
力学原理是什么？
The physics?
物理学？
How does it do that?
它是怎么做到的？
On this episode, we're going to go to SpaceX to see the first rocket to ever land,
本期节目中 我们将前往SpaceX公司 看看第一枚着陆的火箭
meet the king of model rockets and his Falcon Heavy--
见识一下火箭模型之王和他的重型猎鹰火箭 --
Dude! This is not a joke!
老兄  - 这不是开玩笑
--and fly like a Falcon 9.
--以及像一个猎鹰9那样飞行
[尖叫声]
[screams]
I'm going to use a grid fin to steer like a SpaceX rocket.
我打算用格栅翼来转向 就像SpaceX火箭一样
麻麻快看
我是猎鹰9号
I mean, what could go wrong?
我是指 这肯定能行
- ♪ -
TIM: Ever since I was little, I've been obsessed with space.
Tim: 从我小时候起 我就迷上了太空
I'm Tim Dodd, but most people know me as the Everyday Astronaut.
我是Tim Dodd 但大多数人都知道我是每日宇航员
A couple years ago, I bought a spacesuit just for fun.
几年前 我买了一套太空服(高空服)只是为了好玩
I had no idea where that would take me.
我不知道穿这衣服会把我带到哪儿去
- [嗖] - [笑][尖叫声]
- [whoosh] - [laughs]
Woo!
呜
Now I'm a mission to get everyone to nerd out on space.
现在 有个任务我要完成 那就是让每个人都痴迷上太空
和每日宇航员一起发呆
- ♪ -
- MALE REPORTER: In preparation for her maiden voyage--
- 男性记者: 为了准备她的处女航...
航天飞机哥伦比亚号
1981年4月12日
- TIM: The space shuttle program was NASA's first crack at reusable spacecraft.
- Tim: 航天飞机计划是NASA在可重复使用航天器上的第一次尝试
航天飞机哥伦比亚号
1981年4月12日
Unfortunately,
不幸地是
thanks to design compromises and the need to refurbish key components with each and every launch,
由于设计上的妥协 以及每次发射都需要翻新关键部件
1892.7m³液氧
453.6吨固体燃料
24000块隔热瓦
外部燃料储罐
flying and re-flying the reusable space shuttles turned out to be really expensive,
反复发射可重复使用的航天飞机最终变得真的很贵
with the program costing a total of $209 billion.
该计划共耗资2090亿美元
- [收银机叮当声]
- [cash register dings]
- TIM: That's billion with a B.
- Tim: 那可是数以亿计啊
So, NASA grounded the space shuttle program.
所以 NASA停飞了航天飞机项目
Then, along came Space Exploration Technologies, better known as SpaceX.
然后 太空探索技术公司出现了 也就是大家熟知的SpaceX
猎鹰1号
2008年9月28日
- WOMAN: We have liftoff. Falcon has cleared the tower.
- 女声: 起飞 猎鹰号离开了发射塔
猎鹰1号
2008年9月28日
- In 2011, when Elon Musk announced plans for his "little" rocket company to try to reuse rockets,
- 2011年 当马一龙宣布计划让他的小火箭公司尝试重复使用火箭时
most people were pretty skeptical.
大多数人都很怀疑
Then they actually did it.
然后 他们居然做到了
- [笑得很开心]
- [laughs gleefully]
This is that actual rocket.
这就是那枚火箭
On December 21, 2015, this thing took off on Cape Canaveral,
2015年12月21日 这个东西在卡纳维拉尔角起飞了
went up into space, and a few minutes later, came back down to Earth,
上了太空 几分钟后 又回到了地球
marking the first time in human history an orbital-class liquid rocket booster landed.
标志着人类历史上首次轨道级液体火箭助推器着陆
Landing a rocket, of course, means you should be able to reuse the rocket.
着陆火箭 当然意味着你应该能够重复使用火箭
And that is what makes the Falcon 9 so groundbreaking--
这就是猎鹰9号的突破性意义所在
- [打碟声]
- [record screeching]
- TIM: --the fact that you can cost-effectively fly them--
- Tim: -事实上 这样的发射还挺有性价比 --
- [打碟声]
- [record screeching]
- TIM: --land them, then fly them over and over again.
- Tim: -很有性价比地着陆 然后再发射 再如此重复
- [火花咝咝声]
- [spark sizzling]
- TIM: To help us understand just how insanely difficult landing a rocket is,
- Tim: 为了帮助我们了解火箭的着陆有多么的困难
I meet up with Joe Barnard.
我和Joe Barnard见面了
I'm not gonna lie, this is probably the weirdest start to an interview ever.
说实话 这可能是有史以来最奇怪的采访开头
But here's why.
但是让我来解释下原因
Ever since I learned who Joe Barnard is, I've wanted to see his Falcon Heavy.
自从我知道Joe Barnard是谁后 我就想看看他的重型猎鹰火箭
He's the king of model rockets.
他是火箭模型之王
Joe, how are you?
Joe 你好吗？
- What up, Tim?
- 怎么了 Tim?
- Uh...I should probably turn around now, huh?
- 呃... 我现在应该转身了吧?
- I think we're--I think we're go for turnaround.
- 我觉得掉头这个动作可以进行了
- Okay.
- 好
- ♪
- Here it is.
- 就这样吧
[笑]
[laughing]
Oh my gosh, dude! This is not a joke!
哦 我的天哪 伙计 这不是开玩笑
比例：1:48
How big is this?
这有多大？
- JOE: It's a little over a meter tall.
- Joe: 有一米多高
- I didn't know this thing was over a meter tall!
- 我都不知道这东西有一米多高!
Or 3.3 feet tall.
或者3.3英尺高(棒读)
- No, we use metric in aerospace.
- 不 我们在航空航天领域用的是公制
- TIM: Joe is working on getting his 1:48 scale model rocket to land,
- Joe正努力让他的1: 48比例的火箭模型着陆
just like the real thing.
就像真的那个火箭一样
- You know, I can afford to build this scale of rockets.
- 你知道 我有能力建造这种规模的火箭
I just try to make them as complex as possible in the way that the real thing works.
我只是想让它们尽可能的复杂 就像真实的东西一样
- TIM: Okay, so there's a lot of complex rocket science that goes into landing a rocket.
- Tim: 好吧 要解释火箭着陆需要很多复杂的火箭科学知识
- JOE: Something called thrust vectoring.
- Joe: 这就是所谓的推力矢量
And they both get gimbaled at the same time if you're within a certain range of your apogee.
如果远地点在一定范围内 就要让它们同时使用推力矢量(返回) (大概是陆地返场着陆)
And as I'm sure you know, the Falcon 9 uses something called Guidance For Fuel Optimal Landing Divert.
我相信你也知道 猎鹰9号使用的是燃料最佳着陆引导系统
It's actually a pretty simple thing called a third order polynomial.
这其实是一个很简单的东西 叫做三阶多项式
- So, this one has a Tesla on the top?
- 那么 这上面有一个特斯拉？
- JOE: Not right now.
- Joe: 现在还没有
But I'm thinking we should put a Hot Wheels in there.
但我在想我们应该在那里放一辆风火轮小汽车
- TIM: Now, for those of you who don't speak rocket,
- 现在 对于那些不懂火箭的人来说
let me translate what Joe's saying.
让我来翻译一下Joe的说法
This is how a Falcon 9 lands.
这就是猎鹰9号的着陆方式
After stage separation, the hypersonic grid fins deploy.
一二级分离后 高超音速格栅翼展开
Then, cold gas thrusters fire up to reorient the rocket for re-entry.
然后 冷气推进器启动 重新调整火箭的方向 以便再入
They're those white flashes you're seeing.
你看到的那些白色的闪光就是冷气推进器
Three of the rocket's Merlin engines fire up to slow the rocket down as it re-enters the Earth's atmosphere.
三台梅林引擎启动 使火箭在再入地球大气层时减速
Then, the grid fins do their thing to precisely steer the rocket towards the landing pad.
然后 格栅翼精确地控制火箭到着陆场着陆
Another engine fires up, and the landing legs come out.
另一个引擎启动 同时展开着陆腿
Touchdown!
着陆
See, I actually know a thing or two about rocket science.
看吧 我对火箭科学还真有几分了解
- [发动机的轰鸣声]
- [engine blast]
- [机器发出的呼呼声]
- [machine whirring]
- Clearly there's a lot that goes into landing rockets.
- 显然 火箭的着陆有很多讲究
But how hard can it really be?
但这到底有多难呢？
Well, today, I'm determined to find out.
好吧 今天 我决心要找出答案
I'm going to fly and then land just like a Falcon 9.
我要像猎鹰9号一样 先飞起来 再着陆
And although I don't have any Merlin engines...yet,
虽然我还没有任何梅林引擎
I've got the next best thing-- a vertical wind tunnel.
我有另一个同样好的东西  一个垂直风洞
Here to help me fly like a Falcon is science junkie Olivia Pavco Giaccia.
帮助我像猎鹰一样飞翔的是科学迷Olivia Pavco Giaccia
We're about to take to the indoor skies-- --after our safety briefing.
我们就要飞上室内天空了 当然得在安全简报之后
- Realistically, how bad could we get hurt doing this?
- 现实中 我们这样做会伤得多严重？
- Potentially anything you've seen on a football field I've seen in the tunnel.
- 你在足球场上见过的任何东西 我在风洞里都见过
- So, like concussions?
- 所以 比如脑震荡？
- I've been knocked out twice in the tunnel.
- 我在风洞里晕倒过两次
- TIM: Wait, what?
- Tim: 等等 什么？
I'd better take this safety briefing seriously.
我最好认真对待这个安全简报
- INSTRUCTOR: So we're gonna go over a few safety procedures.
- 所以我们要学习一些安全程序
The really important thing to remember is symmetry.
真正重要的是要记住对称性
- TIM: Symmetry?
- Tim: 对称性？
Like the grid fins' X-wing configuration.
像格栅翼的X翼配置
Oh, I love that they made "Star Wars" a real thing.
哦 我喜欢他们把星球大战变成了现实
Ooh, when's the next one coming out?
哦 下一部什么时候出来？
I really liked that last one.
我很喜欢上一部
Wait, I think this guy's almost finished.
等等 我觉得这家伙快讲完了
Uh, ask a follow-up just so he thinks you're paying attention.
问个后续问题让他觉得你在注意听
So how long have you been doing this?
你做这个多久了？
- Um, I've been working here, uh, on and off for 12 years now.
- 嗯 我在这里工作 呃 断断续续12年了
- You're pretty good in there? - Pretty decent, yeah.
- 你在这里干得不错吧？- 相当不错 是的
- TIM: What are the odds that on day one,
- Tim: 第一天的困难有多大？
I outdo you with all these cool flips that I've been working on in my dreams?
你那些翻滚动作难道做得比我梦里的还好吗？
- Astronomically slim.
- 不说好多少 但肯定差不多
- Mm. Mm-hmm.
- 嗯...嗯？
- TIM: I'll take those odds.
- Tim: 好 那我们走着瞧
Now, you may not know this, and I may not look like it,
现在 你可能不知道这一点  我可能看上去也不是这样
but I'm a natural athlete.
但我有运动天赋
And I've got a feeling that flying in a wind tunnel will be a breeze.
而且我感觉在风洞里飞行会很轻松
Obviously, before we land like a Falcon 9,
显然 在我们像猎鹰9号一样着陆之前
we first have to fly like one.
我们首先要像猎鹰9号那样飞行
All the air being generated by the giant fan is pushing us up hard enough to beat gravity.
巨大的风扇产生的空气把我们推上去 足以超过重力
Now, our instructor is pulling and moving us around the wind tunnel.
现在 我们的教练正拉着我们在风洞里移动
But we can also manipulate the air pushing us up by making small adjustments to our bodies.
但我们也可以通过对身体的细微调整来操控抬起我们的空气
Small, teeny-tiny movements to our arms, legs, and torso alter the direction of lift and allow us to steer.
手臂 腿部和躯干的微小动作改变了升力的方向 从而进行转向
Considering this is our first flight,
考虑到这是我们的第一次飞行
I'd say Olivia and I are doing pretty good.
我想说 Olivia和我做得很好
That was freaking awesome.
这感觉妙极了
And as you can tell, I'm really good at it.
你也可以看出 我真的很在行(迫真)
But the whole point of this is for science.
但这一切的目的是为了科学
We're trying to figure out how to land a rocket.
我们想知道火箭是怎么着陆的
To really experience what it's like to land a rocket,
为了真正体验一下火箭着陆的感觉
I brought my human-sized, garage-engineered grid fin.
我带来了我的人类大小的 自家制造的格栅翼
And like a Falcon 9, I'm gonna use it to steer me.
像猎鹰9号一样 我要用它来控制我的姿态
- Help me understand.
- 跟我说说
What is it that makes grid fins better than regular fins?
是什么让格栅翼比普通机翼更好？
- TIM: The big thing about a grid fin is that it can be deployed as it comes back down into the atmosphere.
- Tim: 格栅翼的最大特点是它可以在返回大气层时展开
All of a sudden, you have wings.
突然间 你有了机翼
'Cause on the way up, you don't really want wings.
因为在上升的过程中 你并不真正想要机翼
- [蜂鸣器]
- [buzzer]
- And what is it about the grid fins' grid formation?
- 那格栅翼的网格形态是起什么作用呢？
- TIM: There are, basically, hundreds of little wings tucked in there.
- Tim: 基本上 相当于有几百个小翼塞在里面
It's a way to be compact.
这是一种紧凑的方式
You also can apply a lot of torque,
(通过这么多翼面) 你也可以施加很大的扭矩
but not a lot of movement that needs to happen to turn and rotate.
却不需要对格栅翼本身进行很大的转动 就能控制箭体的偏航和滚转
Even at idle speeds, the wind is really, really strong.
即使是在怠速的情况下 风速也真的非常大
How fast is it the wind going right now?
现在的风速有多少？
- Our idle speed is 900 RPMs.
- 我们的空转速度是900转/分
Our reach speed tops out at 2,100 RPMs-- about 110 miles an hour.
能到达的最高速度是2100转/分钟 大约49.17m/s(177km/h)
- Even at this slow speed, that has a lot of effect.
- 即使是这么慢的速度 也有很大的影响
Okay, things are about to get real.
好了 接下来这事儿就要成真了
随着风速的加大
它对我的影响越来越大
我的妈耶
这就是猎鹰9号(着陆)的工作原理
基本上，猎鹰9号有四个像这样的格栅翼
然后它会像这样工作
并控制它自身的姿态
这种控制方式真奇怪
This is not a SpaceX-approved explanation of their technology.
这并不是SpaceX认可的技术解释
麻麻快看
我是猎鹰9号
[尖叫声]
- [screeches]
But in order to complete my Falcon transformation,
但为了完成我的猎鹰变形
I've gotta launch.
我要发射了
I need to blast off, and then use my grid fin to elegantly
我需要像火箭那样起飞 然后用我的格栅翼控制升力的方向
and accurately steer myself from the tunnel by manipulating my direction of lift.
来优雅地精确地操控我身体在风洞里的姿态
Ready? Here we go.
准备好了吗？开始了
In three, two, one...
三 二 一...
And we have liftoff.
起飞
I'm flying like a Falcon 9...sorta.
四舍五入 我算是像猎鹰9号一样飞行了吧
I'm not really getting up as high as I thought I would.
我并没有像我想象的那样飞得很高
Just trying to hang on to this grid fin,
只是想抓紧这个格栅翼
it's a lot harder than it looks.
它比看起来要难得多
Every tiny bit of movement I make creates a lot of torque thanks to the grids on my grid fin.
我做的每一个微小的动作都会产生很大的扭矩 这要归功于我的格栅翼上的栅格
It's really hard to hang on, much less steer with this thing.
要坚持下去真的很难 更不用说用这个东西转向了
Fun fact: it took SpaceX more than five years and several failed attempts to land their first Falcon 9 rocket.
有趣的是 SpaceX花了五年多的时间和几次失败的尝试 才让第一枚猎鹰9号火箭着陆
Yeah, that's a lot of fail.
是啊 这里面失败过很多次
So, I guess I'm in good company.
所以我想我也会遇到一样的问题
Well, our instructor wants to give it a go.
好吧 我们的教练想试一试
Hmph, good luck.
哼哼 祝你好运
- ♪
- TIM: Whoa, this guy is good!
- Tim: 哇 这家伙真厉害
Our mild-mannered wind tunnel instructor's flying around like Superman.
我们脾气温和的风洞教练像超人一样来回飞行
He's turning himself by making small adjustments to the grid fin's angle and redirecting lift,
他通过对格栅翼的角度做微小的调整来改变自己的方向 重新改变升力的方向
just like a Falcon 9.
就像猎鹰9号一样
Yes, yes! Our grid fin works!
是的没错 我们的格栅翼能用
Well, we learned the hard way that landing rockets is super difficult.
好吧 为了证明着陆火箭是超级困难的 我们吃了不少亏
No wonder it took nearly a century to figure it out.
难怪花了近一个世纪才弄明白
So, here's to all those genius rocket scientists that make it look easy.
那么 感谢那些让它看起来很容易的天才火箭科学家们
Good luck, Joe Barnard.
祝你好运 Joe Barnard
That's gonna do it for me.
节目到这里就结束了
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people.
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
For more out-of-this-world content,
更多棒得很的内容
be sure and follow us on Facebook Watch.
别关注了，2018年6月13日之后就没有更新了
要记得到Facebook Watch上关注我们哦